Guide to the Eda Edson papers, 1930-1976
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Eda Edson papers
1930-1976
C0218
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
The Eda Edson papers contain personal papers collected by Edson from the 1930s to 1976. These papers include newspaper clippings highlighting her work in vaudeville in the early 1930s, correspondence regarding connections to the Federal Theatre Project, photographs of Edson and her orchestra, as well as scripts, production notes, and programs from the production Follow the Parade.
Arrangement
Organized alphabetically by folder title.
Scope and Content
The Eda Edson Federal Theatre Project papers contain personal papers collected by Edson from the 1930s to 1976. These papers include newspaper clippings highlighting her work in vaudeville in the early 1930s, correspondence regarding connections to the Federal Theatre Project, photographs of Edson and her orchestra, as well as scripts, production notes, and programs from the production Follow the Parade.
Biographical Information
The Federal Theatre Project was a division of the Works Progress Administration (WPA), which provided employment for large numbers of artists, writers, and performers during the Great Depression (1929-1939). The Federal Theatre began in 1935 and, until its end in 1939, flourished as the first and only federally sponsored and subsidized theater program in the United States. Directed by Hallie Flanagan (1880-1969), it was a way for theatrical professionals to gain employment during the Depression.
The number of unemployed theatre workers in Los Angeles was second only to those in New York. Eda Edson worked on the Los Angeles Federal Theatre Project productions "Follow the Parade" and "The Black Crook." Under the direction of Eda Edson, formerly employed in vaudeville as a conductor, the variety unit wrote the sketches, lyrics, and music of "Follow the Parade." Part topical revue, part circus, part dramatic show, it ran in Los Angeles for ten weeks before large audiences, and then was taken to the Texas Centennial in Dallas, where it played for the rest of the summer in 1936. Edson later went on to more conducting work, and in 1953 she authored the short self help guide "The world is your stage...learn how to be the leading lady: How acting in everyday life will reveal the vivid, lovely, effective you."
Alternative Form Available
There are digital documents from this and other GMU FTP collections in the.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Eda Edson to Special Collections and Archives May 30, 1976.
Related Material
The Works Progress Administration oral histories collection, the Federal Theatre Project collection, the Federal Theatre Project photograph collection, as well as numerous other personal papers.
Index Terms
Persons:
Edson, Eda
Corporate Names:
Federal Theatre Project (U.S.); Federal Theatre Project (Los Angeles, Calif.)
Subjects:
New Deal, 1933-1939.; Music--20th century.; Performing arts.; Theater--United States.
Contents List
- Eda Edson papers, 1930-1976
  - Correspondence, 1960s-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Federal Theatre, circa 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Programs for Follow the Parade; copies of correspondence and resignation letter regarding Federal Theatre and Follow the Parade; one page of sheet music; costume design sketch; photocopy of Los Angeles Federal Theatres volume 1 number 1; photocopies of photographs depicting Edson, theatres, and stages.
    - Excerpt from Eda Edson oral history interview
  - Follow the Parade, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Programs for The Black Crook, Follow the Parade, The first performance of the Federal Theatre project staff of W.P.A. region number 5; synopsis of Follow the Parade; production number Crazy House Suite; synopsis for On a Holiday; notes for Follow the Parade; resignation letter.
    - Follow the Parade
  - Follow the Parade, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Production notes / script.
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Newspaper clippings, advertisements, correspondence about Edson's work before the Federal Theatre Project; Follow the Parade program, telegrams; articles about female conductors; handmade artwork/letters sent to Edson; photocopies of Federal Theatre correspondence regarding Black Crook.
  - Oscar material, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Photocopies from unknown publication about Oscar winners; typed notes on Di Maggio, and conductors; eight photographs of movie stars "before and after".
  - Photographs, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Photographs of Edson; Edson and orchestra; one photograph with cardboard backing of Edson during a performance; one photograph on cardboard backing with unidentified people.
    - Eda Edson with orchestra
  - Programs, circa 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Power; Follow the Parade; The Black Crook; Los Angeles Federal Theatres vol. 1 no. 1.
  - Scrapbook pages, 1930s-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Scrapbook pages with newspaper articles, correspondence, and telegrams. One black and white photograph possibly of Edson.
    - Telegram from Hallie Flanagan
    - Telegram from George Gerwing to Eda Edson
  - Write Dammit!, undated; 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Newspaper clipping; blank greeting card; note to Edson encouraging her to write.